Downloaded from
YTS.MX
Official YIFY movies site:
- This piece of water we're
gonna fish, it's a thicket.
The casting is very demanding
in this tight brush.
I don't think that this cast
and this type of fishing has
ever really been recorded.
Come on, control it.
If we can capture this on film today,
it will be a highlight.
This is not gonna be an easy day
but it's gonna be a great one.
To catch a brook trout in
all its wriggled beauty,
it's gold to me.
- I am Joe Humphreys.
I am 86 years old,
86 years young.
It took me about two and a
half years to write this book
and so many times when
I was writing that book,
I hit the wall and the
way I got around that,
I just picked up the fly
rod, head for the stream,
work a patch of water and said,
"Oh, this is what I want to say."
- I'm a professional fly fisherman
here in Central Pennsylvania
and these streams
are some of my favorites
to fish in all the world.
I've been fishing since
I was six years old.
From that moment on, I
have lived, breathed,
taught and competed in the
wonderful sport of fly fishing.
- Fly fishing is a form of fishing where
instead of using live bait like worms,
you mimic bugs with materials
such as fur and feathers.
The fly is cast into
the water with a fly rod
and propelled by the weight of a line.
Well, isn't that neat?
That is beautiful.
After 80 years, I can't
imagine doing anything else.
Oh, ho, ho, ho, that's a nice fish.
You might as well get
this 'cause Ranger Rick,
if I still have that fish,
I'm gonna get him one way or the other.
When I hook a big fish
or I hook a fish at night
or anytime I'm fishing
and I get into a fish,
the little boy comes back.
- Oh, did he get off?
- It was a big brown trout, a
brown trout about that long.
That was a brown trout about 14 inches.
Oh well.
It's no coincidence that my
life has always been enchanted
by a beautiful creature
that's tough to catch, a fish.
- I have made fly
fishing my livelihood.
I've taught thousands of students
over a period of many years.
I will continue to teach until
I've finally reached the
bottom of that mountain.
- My dad has accomplished
so much in his life
and he is really famous
in the fishing world.
Almost every place we go
or any place we travel,
we will meet people who know him.
He's fished in pretty
much every state in the US
and that includes Alaska,
he's done World Championships.
He's traveled all over the world fishing.
But my dad does everything
when it comes to teaching fly fishing.
- My purpose and intent of this video
is to have you enjoy this
sport to its fullest.
The line is in motion and fling it.
The back two fingers pull.
- He did the first fly
fishing series ever on ESPN.
- "Fly Fishing Journal"
with your host, Joe Humphreys.
- Today on "Fly Fishing journal,"
I have with me, my special
guest George Harvey.
George and I have been
fishing many years together
and it's a real pleasure for me to have
my mentor on the stream
with me on this Spring-
- We'll meet people who will say
"I learned so much through
watching his videos."
- Fish along with me this morning
and maybe we can catch a couple fish.
Maybe we can get really
lucky and catch three.
- His books meant
everything to me when I was growing up.
He does fly fishing shows, clinics.
- When I'm through with this
demo, you'll be so screwed up,
you won't know which
end of the rod to hold.
So that's fair warning.
- I always think there's
nothing left to do
but he always says there's
that one more book in him.
There's one more video in him.
There's always something
else that can be done.
- To me, one of
his biggest contributions
is all the charity work he does.
- Do I have all
my little students here?
- Yes.
- Hello.
- Hello there.
- For him, it's not about fame or glory.
He feels that he's been given this gift
and he needs to give it to other people.
- What happens to
people if they don't have
proper instruction and they
don't have any direction
and they try unsuccessfully on their own,
frustrations build, "I'll try golf."
When you have instruction
and nothing succeeds
like success and you say,
"Whoa, this is kind of fun."
When you catch a fish,
you're off and running.
You never forget it.
- Are those just sticks?
- Taking the second right.
- That he glued together?
- Going over the stream.
- That's a catus.
- Oh, it is a catus, cool.
- Who would have every
thought that that little fellow
would've been built of that
complete house of sticks.
- He was amazing to go hike with
and I guess I thought
everyone's dad was this way.
He would be able to
tell you whatever tracks
you saw, what animal it
was or respect of nature.
- You thought
everyone's dad was like that?
- Oh, I thought everyone's
dad was like that.
Then I realized other
people's dads were in office
buildings in the summer and
not doing those kind of things.
- You got a bright future, honey.
- Thank you very much.
- Good.
What got me hooked on fly fishing?
The interest, it was almost
innate, it was there.
I was born with it.
I've always felt strongly
about a piece of water,
a stream, like it's almost
running through my system
and my body and I think that
started at such a tender age.
I loved to play in the water.
I loved to wade in the water.
I loved to look for things in the water
and so it was just a natural.
It all started when my father
moved us from Curwensville, Pennsylvania.
This house was my family home
and in that second floor
is where we were all born
and I was born January 19th, 1929.
Those were the Great Depression years.
My father had lost his job in
a bank. They were hard years.
So in 1935, we moved to State College
because my father wanted
his children to be educated
and he got a job in the Bursar's Office
at Penn State University
and my life changed.
But that's where it started.
That move, it was a weird twist of fate.
Yes, I got my BS degree and my Masters
in Education and it's what I wanted to do.
But little did my father realize
that he also gave me my livelihood.
State College was the mecca of fly fishing
because of Fishermans Paradise,
a piece of Spring Creek developed
in 1934 for fly fishing only.
This was the first all fly fishing
project in the United
States, if not the world.
With this piece of water, fly fishing
was something to learn
about and something to do.
We have more trout streams
in Pennsylvania than
I think any other State in
the Union, other than Alaska.
Central Pennsylvania is limestone country.
Not only is the area rich in nutrients,
the runoff from the mountains, the hills,
the freestone streams go
down into the valleys.
A lot of the streams go underground
and come up as major springs.
The clear, cold, top
of the mountain water.
The trout population, their metabolism
demands temperatures into
the 50s, 60s to survive.
This is why we have such wonderful
trout waters in the area,
because of the beautiful big springs
that keep our waters clear and cold.
The mountains, the streams, the resources
were so wonderful and so
the State College area
was an important aspect of my life.
We are going after some cold spring water.
That water is absolutely delightful
and that's what I have in my coffee here.
So that's my coffee water in the mornings.
It's cold spring water that
come right out of the mountains.
Nothing added.
I can't find any better water
than what I have right here.
And off we go to the happy lands.
We are now following the
main stream of Spring Creek.
My father took me to Spring
Creek when I was a child.
I was six years old.
Neither of us had ever fished
or picked up a fishing rod.
We were fishing worms
with bamboo fly rods.
And my first cast, the worm
luckily landed in the water
and then I felt a tug and I
pulled and out came a trout and
it flew up over my head and
landed in the weeds behind me.
That didn't take long.
I was so excited and lo and behold,
there was an eight inch
trout, a native brown.
I was just in awe of
the beauty of that fish.
The halos, the spots.
So this is the beginning and after
my first experience with
my father, it was a quest.
Here's another one.
It really stuck with me.
I wanted to fish.
You might say that I was self-taught.
My early efforts were very clumsy
but I had the patience of Job.
This is where I caught some
of my very first trout.
I guess you could call this
one of my major classrooms.
When I was probably eight, 10,
I would get on my bicycle,
fly rod across the handlebar
and I would pedal, pedal to Thompson Run.
Thompson Run is a
tributary of Spring Creek.
There was so much I
learned from Thompson Run.
I would view trout,
watch them feed readily.
Where they went, how they lifted,
how they positioned themselves.
It was like they were
laying out a plan for me.
How would I capture these fish?
How could I catch one of these?
- The most amazing thing to
me about what Joe has done,
79 years ago, there was no
internet, there were no videos,
there wasn't a library
of books to learn from.
- My childhood pictures.
- This guy has figured it out on his own.
- Take a look at these.
I tell a story about catching
this fish out of Thompson Run
and I had tried to catch
this trout at earlier times
and he disappeared through my clumsiness.
After the last time I spooked that fish,
I waded into the water
and I grabbed a handful
of vegetation and it was alive
with freshwater shrimp and
some of these shrimp had a
little touch of orange on them.
I found some orange sewing
thread in my mother's
sewing basket and with some
fur and that sewing thread,
I fashioned what I thought
was something that looked like it.
I went back to the stream,
got into position and made
the cast and the fish traveled
a few feet for that fly.
It was a 14 inch fish, one of
the biggest I had ever taken.
Now I knew it took the fly underneath
as well as on top and
this is called nymphing.
I pedaled my bicycle home with that prize
and my mother took a picture of that fish.
The trout streams of State
College, they were my classroom,
my playground, they were like coming home.
I still live in State College
because in my 25 mile radius,
there are several streams you can fish.
All the special water that
held a lot of memories for me.
Henge Creek, Fishing Creek
and the little Juning Ladder.
Thompson Run down here and Spring Creek.
Oh, donuts this morning. Well thank you.
How do you like that coffee this morning?
- Wonderful as always.
- But Spring Creek is my lifeline.
Spring Creek flows 22 miles from a source
near my home in the
mountains of the Tussey Ridge
and its confluence with a
Bald Eagle Creek in Milesburg.
Spring Creek means everything to me.
It's my childhood, my parents
and my siblings
but also my wife
and children.
Gloria and I raised our
family on this stream
because it runs behind my property.
I have two wonderful
daughters, Johanna and Dolores
and Dolores, she was in one
of my ESPN shows with me.
- And featuring
special guest, Dolores Humphreys.
- I guess the last time we were together
really and spending much
time on the stream at all
was when you had my angling
class at Penn State University.
- That right.
He went out West or a
time after high school
and helped build the
Million Dollar Highway
in Colorado and he
fished the Dolores River.
I'm even named after a river
and Johanna is named after him.
- Both girls have made me so proud.
Little Johanna being a track champion.
- I don't have the fishing
connection with my dad.
I have the athletic connection.
We're both pretty strong-willed
and pretty stubborn
and it's always been a competition.
Even as a kid, he would challenge
me to races in the yard.
You know, 'cause he
really wanted to beat me.
He's a character.
- The secret of my
longevity is whole milk.
I drink milk like it's going out of style.
I've never had a broken bone and I've been
in every kind of undesirable
situation and no broken bones
and then I ate a lot of fish in my life.
When I was a kid, I fished a
lot and that's what we ate.
This is the Joe Humphreys, we're hungry,
We threw a trout in the
pan, we cook it, we eat it.
My trout sandwich.
Yeah baby.
Life is good.
- No tattoos?
- No, I never had a tattoo.
But I have something of that
fashion I guess you might say.
I have a golden trout on in my tooth.
- How old were
you when you got that?
- Oh, who knows? Probably in my 60s.
- And then there's Denny.
My sister and I rely on Denny now
as an even bigger part of my dad's life.
- Denny is the
brother that we never had.
- Denny is like my son, we're so close.
- He was fishing on
our stream many years ago and
did not see the no trespassing
sign and he met my mother.
Fast-forward a dozen years
later and he is someone
that's incredibly important to our family.
- Because of Gloria,
I get to fish with Jo,
we get to go to dinner with the girls,
spend Christmas together,
our families are very close.
A lot of people have
asked me over the years,
"Summarize Joe as a fly fishermen."
It's almost impossible.
Throw him on a small mountain stream where
you've got no room to cast and he throws
a Humpy up in there and takes
an eight inch brook trout.
- Yay.
- The same day, you
could go to a big limestone
in Central Pennsylvania
and he'll drift nymph stone
on the bottom and pick
fish off the bottom.
- I said I was gonna take
another one before I get outta there.
- There's one.
- That's a better fish.
- Yeah, that's what I wanted.
- You go out that night at 2:00
in the morning in the dark of the moon
and he'll swing big wet
flies and catch a behemoth.
- Yeah, I have it, you sucker.
I couldn't get him in the net in there.
It's a good fish. It's a nice big fish.
Yeah, you think the old
man can't still catch fish?
- I've been a fan of his since
he caught his State Record
brown trout in the dark.
- Go ahead and tell
us of your State Record.
- Oh, the story?
- Yeah.
- It's late evening, I'm
fishing a big, long, deep pool
and I hear a tremendous explosion
and it went stone quiet.
I knew it had to be a heck of a fish.
I almost got a divorce over this one
because I stalked the
fish for three years,
going night after night after night.
Gloria saying "You're fishing"
And I told her about this fish.
One night, my telephone rang
and it was my buddy Al Hag
and he said, "Hey Hump, I'm antsy.
Why don't you go fishing?
I'll just go along."
And I said, "Okay, Al."
So I went back to the pool and I went down
through the first time and
I took a pretty nice fish,
18, 19 and it was okay but I was excited
because now it's 1:00 morning.
He said to me, "Don't you
think it's time to go home?"
I said, "Just let me run this
top end just one more time."
And I chucked those two
flies across that stream
in that backwater and
I gave 'em a little tip
to get those flies into
motion and all at once,
they stopped and the
rod tip goes .
It sounded like somebody
rolled a Wurst tub over
and I put the hammer to
this fish, I was just
almost out of line and I
stopped the fish on the run.
I had no net, a net wouldn't
have landed that fish anyhow
and Al said "Oh my god, I've
never seen a fish this big."
and I said, "Neither have I,
I think I've got a record."
The ward measured it, it was a
16 pound 34 inch brown trout.
The previous record was 33.
For 11 years, it was
Pennsylvania's record trout.
It is still the fly-caught
record brown trout
for trout in Pennsylvania
and probably a lot of States.
That's the story of the big fish.
I think of that fish often
but I've always wanted a 20 pound brown.
That's been my drive through life.
I want a World Record
and this is one reason
that I really got into the night game.
- God bless you.
- See you, sir. Thank you.
- Thank you.
- Joe, he's famous for night fishing.
- We've got some fans.
Night fishing to me is
one of my favorite games.
It's when the heavyweights
come out to feed.
Your big trout, World Record
fish, they're nocturnal.
These two patterns, I call
'em my stonefly patterns.
These flies are big, they move water.
They represent large
insects like a stonefly.
We're gonna go give these a try and see
if we can't find something
larger than a foot long.
So here we go.
Follow the blind here,
Denny.
Here's a tip for anybody fishing at night.
Never go on a stream that you don't know
after dark because it
can be very dangerous.
You can lose your life.
- Whoa, watch these thistles.
Night fishing, it's not for everybody.
I mean it's tripping and
falling, getting lost, snakes.
Joe has a great story about
stepping on a rattlesnake
whacking his waders in
the middle of the dark.
It is not as easy as he makes it look.
It is a lifetime of work
that he's put into this.
- Your casting stroke
and your casting ability comes into play.
Okay, lights out.
It's called pinpoint casting in darkness.
You have to know when to
squeeze that stroke off
to get back under those
trees and next to that bank
and if you don't spot that
fly in the very few inches,
it's difficult to take them.
I got a big fish. Oh,
I got a fish, fish on.
When you have the take
of a large fish at night
and you feel that heavy weight
and the power of a fish,
it's truly exciting because you don't know
on the take, how big that fish is.
It could be 20 inches,
it could be 20 pounds.
Are you getting any of this battle?
Are you getting any of this?
Do you want to see a big fish at night?
There's a big fish at night.
It's called credibility.
Don't talk about it if you can't do it.
- How about that, huh?
- What a day.
The fact that you become
known for some expertise
in your field, that's wonderful
but I think as a teacher,
you want to be as well-versed
as you possibly can.
You owe it to your students.
I have traveled extensively
and have had the privilege
of working with so many
people and teaching so long
and I'm still so busy teaching.
- Any given week, he's gone at least
three-quarters of the
week teaching a class.
- July still has a couple open dates
and August still has a couple open dates
but otherwise this entire
schedule book is filled.
- I'm moving all the time,
going so many different places.
When you get old, you
think old, you're old.
86,
that's just a number.
- How many miles do
you think you drive in a month?
- It's hard to say.
I have a hard time saying
no to a lot of good causes.
What I don't like is driving
to Somerset, New Jersey.
It's called Demolition Derby.
Okay everybody, pull in with the old man.
Back to basics, I am a left-hander,
so I drop down on my right knee.
I will need help getting back.
The reason I'm on my knee
is because I want my arm out of the game.
We're gonna let the rod work.
You're gonna lift up into
it, stop it and tap it.
Push your thumb down and we're casting.
That little pressure,
pushing the thumb down here,
now you don't rotate and move.
I'm one of the few guys in
the profession that don't mind
going on a stream and working
for fish in front of people.
- Joe makes fly fishing look so easy.
He's never failed taking
fish with us and we've
put him in some extreme
conditions during the 22 years
- To be stewards of a stream,
you're gonna practice catch-release.
There's your first
little trout of the year.
Hold on, I'll have another one.
And I don't like to handle the fish.
Now I know there's times
you gotta show your buddy
that fish but you don't
have to handle it though.
How many in here have never caught a fish?
How many in here want to catch a fish?
You're at the right
place at the right time.
The Jesse Arnelle group of children
are mostly from the cities who never get
a chance to fish and
enjoy the great outdoors.
- Good one.
- That's insane.
- It'll be a good day if
everybody come and fish.
This is my first time fishing.
My dad fishes all the time,
so I wanted to give a try.
- We got him, we got a fish.
This is fantastic.
- This is amazing.
- Wow.
Look at this.
Wow, your first trout?
- My first trout.
- Oh, what a beauty. Look
at the pretty colors.
- Yes. Oh my gosh, this is just amazing.
I'm just like in a whole
'nother space right now
because of my fish.
- That's how I felt.
- My first fish.
- I hope teaching these kids something
about what the environment
means to all of us
when they saw the beauty
of this world around them,
the beauty of the fish that they caught.
Without clean water in which
these fish live, we're in bad shape.
You got a challenge.
You gotta take care of these
streams that you so enjoy
and you gotta take care of
this land 'cause there's a hell
of a lot of people out
there that won't protect it.
Here's one right here.
- That's awesome.
That's a polyphemus moth.
- Yeah, that's a good one.
Today I'm working with
the Brookings School.
These children, they are learning
the ins and the outs of conservation
of the aquatic insects within the waters
and what they mean to the
trout and its survival.
I would have loved to
have had that opportunity.
It took me 80 years to figure out
the same thing that these
kids are learning in one week.
Who, there's a nice big sculpin.
You know, that's strawberry
shortcake for a trout.
- Yeah.
- I like this.
- Yeah, me too.
- Have you heard
of Joe Humphreys before?
- Yes I have, I've
actually seen his display
in the Fly Fishing Hall of
Fame down in Boiling Springs
and it's definitely a great honor
to be with a real living legend.
The brook trout serve as fabulous
bio-indicators for a lot
of our mountain streams
and cold water streams
here in Pennsylvania.
They're very sensitive to pollution.
A lot of the same streams that these
brook trout are inhabiting are the same
streams where we get
our drinking water from.
So they really do serve as an early
detector of poor water quality for us.
- How does it make
you feel to see these kids so excited?
I mean it has to remind you of you, right?
- Oh my god, it does.
It takes me back to my childhood
and my feet would not
have touched the ground
for probably a month, I
would have been so excited.
So yeah, I understand these kids.
I understand where they're coming from.
When I was a young lad, I did
not enjoy going to school.
Fisticuffs, yes, hard knocks, yes.
I became a problem.
Fishing was the catalyst that moved me
from the depth of despair
into a whole new life.
The Christmas of 1941, my parents,
being so frustrated with
their son, bought me
a book called "Just Fishing"
written by Ray Bergman.
"Just Fishing" by Ray
Bergman and Fred Everett.
That book turned my life around.
I wrote this so that
nobody would steal my book
and I even have my phone number .
This very first chapter
was so influential.
"My first experience trout fishing dates
back to the year of 1903
when I was a boy of 12.
I saw my first living trout in a brook.
I had been wandering
through the woodlands near
my home and by some chance,
had approached a pool
of a small brook without
disturbing its occupants.
As I looked over the bank,
I saw six spotted beauties
spanning their fins in
the cool, clear water.
The sight of those fish
reacted on my nervous system strangely.
I did not know what they were but some
latent instinct within
my being informed me
that they were game to be prized highly."
Now if the teacher were to
ask me to write a paper,
now I had some direction and
I would write maybe about the
brown trout or I'd write about
how to fish with a wet fly.
Even look, I even put little
X's where these flies were
because those were the flies
I thought were important
and those were the ones I wanted to tie.
He had the real basic fundamentals
he had within these pages,
I learned from this.
That book gave me a new start on life.
Hopefully my books,
I hope maybe they give somebody direction.
- I'm most proud of my dad
for who he is to other people.
It's not just that he's
this famous fisherman.
Somebody can say to me, "My
son got to meet your dad
for 10 minutes and it was
a wonderful experience."
And that sums it up of
who he is as a person.
- Kids are the future
of this wonderful sport.
Good morning, look at
these guys right here.
This is a tough crew right here.
Somebody told me you took 47
fish yesterday, is that right?
- Me?
- "Who, me?"
Today I'm in Lamar, Pennsylvania.
It's a beautiful sight up here.
To teach a youth fly fishing team.
You don't need heavy
diameters if you cast right.
What you have to have is line
and leader control, so
that's where we start.
You have to adjust for everything you do.
These children in the last two years,
they've won the Worlds Championships.
All right, we're ready to go.
You gotta remember, I'm a left-hander.
- There's legendary people
in the sport of fly fishing
and Joe is one of the
last ones that is around
still helping and still doing things.
You know what he's talking
is legit and it's gonna work.
- These kids are really tuned in.
They're so fun to teach.
I want that rod to stop right
up and down, 12 o'clock.
- Joe is phenomenal.
He is just upbeat, wants you
to learn as a fly fisherman.
Wants you to get better.
- Stay here with me.
- He's gonna do
anything he can to make you better.
- Okay, here we go.
- Now this is where the game changes.
On a bow and arrow cast, your fly
should always be seven
inches below your handle.
- He teaches us.
- There's your roll cast.
- But then we teach everybody else
and you may talk to a guy
who lives in North Carolina,
who lives all the way in California but
they know his methods from somebody who
learned it from somebody
who learned it from him.
It just keeps getting passed down.
- When he does something,
he wants to do it well
but he really has so
many different talents.
He boxed for the Navy and at Penn State
and here's something a
lot of people don't know,
he was a very good ice
skater and he taught
advanced ice skating as a
Phys Ed course at Penn State.
- When my mother taught
beginning ice skating.
So at any given time, you
could go up to the rink
and find both of them teaching a class.
- He actually was in an
ice show where he did
an ice dance with his fishing
rod, which was amazing.
- Joe Humphreys.
- There's nothing he doesn't do.
Even at 86, even when he's tired.
- He is still in better shape
than most people I know who
are in their 40s and 50s and
pretty much every morning,
he'll go down in the
basement and do his crunches
and his pushups, he calls
it I believe pumping steel.
- I still pump steel.
I work out.
Don't sit and watch the tube.
Stay busy.
Move.
- Awesome.
- When I was fighting,
I used to train with rope.
- It's not a surprise I think
that he's still as agile
physically as he is because
he did all of these sports.
Like I said, it wasn't a passing fad.
It wasn't a membership
at a gym for a year.
This was a way of life.
- He taught almost every Phys Ed course
there was at Penn State
including racquetball,
weightlifting, personal
defense, judo and bowling.
- I mean he was a really good wrestler too
and wrestling coach and was
well-known for that as well.
- He wrestled for
Penn State and in the Navy.
He's already inducted into
the United States Wrestling Hall of Fame.
He still goes into the room today because
he was Penn State's
Assistant Wrestling Coach.
- Look at that strength.
These arms have reeled in
a few fish, probably what?
- When you're ready.
- I'd say 10 fish?
I can't give you that, not
with the camera running.
- These are my heroes,
Cael Sanderson, Casey
Cunningham, Jake Varner,
Cody Sanderson.
- Dang, strong hips.
- Not only the finest
coaches in this nation today,
they're teaching these kids moral values,
they're teaching 'em how to face life.
What you do on the mat as
a coach or a teacher in
the classroom extends far
beyond the mat or the classroom.
It extend into their lives.
- I wrestled for Joe
Humphreys from 1965 to '69.
- Okay, Grant you're here
and you're sitting down.
That is a great shot.
- A monumental man in my life.
He came in at a time when
we needed some direction.
The direction I was on,
it was quitting school.
- If you guys wouldn't have
wrestled today, I would have
been saying "Oh, I wonder
what cell the Packers are in?"
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- I look at him and I think
there should've been three of 'em.
This man changed my life when he said,
"You're gonna be a great one."
Started me in a direction
that was so powerful
that even when I made the wrong choice,
his words stayed with me.
I give him credit all the time.
- I think my dad has
always followed his calling.
They were different
things at different times
and he has always known that fishing
is what his life's work is to be.
- Choosing between
wrestling and fly fishing,
it was a decision that I knew
would really affect my life.
Fishing I guess you might
say was in my blood.
I would never discard it.
It was always there
and it had to be there.
But when I found out
that I could make money
in the five fishing world collegiately
as an instructor at Penn
State, there was no choice.
I gave up wrestling and continued
in the fly fishing world.
My mentor George Harvey, he was a hero.
He was an angler that had
more insights than anybody
I think in the United States or the world.
He created a tuck cast
that got the nips to fish.
They created fly tying
clinics, he was a pioneer.
I learned so much from him and
we were also great friends.
When George Harvey retired from
the angling program at Penn State in 1970,
then I chose to go that direction
and teach the fly fishing
courses at Penn State University.
Penn State angling class started
as a noncredit class in 1934.
It was not an accredited class until 1947.
And I was there 19 years.
How lucky I've been to make
the love of my life my profession.
There, that's a great shot.
With fly fishing, you're
imitating insects.
You're imitating the food chain
in which the trout feed upon.
This is a heldermike,
that's a larval stage
of an insect and is lunch
and dinner for trout.
How many aspects of this
fly fishing game are there?
So many.
This is a stonefly. It has
two wing cases and two tails.
This nymph that you see right now,
they crawl from the stream bottom,
crawl up on the vegetation
or on the rocks and fly away.
There are so many
insects that they inhale.
This is a Caddis Pupa, C-A-D-D-I-S.
They build this case around
them and it's an amazing thing.
We can tie these, imitate
them and they catch fish.
He's wider and lighter and so the fly
that I'm imitating is
the dark part is the case
and the little white
is the head coming out
like the caddis is crawling
out, this is a good imitation.
That's another part about
the game that's so much fun
is that you can find this stuff
on the bottom of the rocks
and then you go back to
the vice and you tie a fly,
tie and you tie until
you get exactly what you
think it is and then you go
out and try it and it works.
To catch a fish on
something that you made with
your own hand to imitate
a glorious little insect,
it's a great feeling.
Isn't nature wonderful?
When I'm fishing with
people, one thing I say
to them at one point
during the day, "Look up."
You've been staring at the water
from the moment we made the first cast.
I like to stop and live the moment.
One of the most beautiful
sounds in the spring
to me is a red-winged
blackbird and its song.
Or it can simply be the
change of the clouds above.
It can simply be the
sun reflecting on a log
and those are cherished moments.
The good Lord has given us
such a beautiful place to fish.
When you don't take time to recognize
and enjoy it and appreciate
it and be thankful,
then you're missing part of the game.
This was a gristmill built back in 1822.
I picked it up 50 years ago,
tried to put it back
together and it's most unique
because it has the
water running underneath
the living room to a pond
with trout in it, I love it.
My brother Dick lived in
the adjoining property
and I thought how nice someday it would be
to be with my brother and
restore that old mill.
What a guy he was.
He was in the Merchant
Marines in World War II.
When he came back, we
started to fish together,
we started to do things together.
We called each other the brothers
and he was instrumental in
helping me with this home.
At the tender age of 47,
he was killed in a tractor accident
in the field adjacent to me
and it was a terrible loss.
- He missed his brother terribly
and his mother died when he was only about
college age and he was
very close to his mother
and he gets very upset easily with death
and it's easy for us to all say "Oh,
well you have all of us,
we're all still here."
But having his wife go before him,
which he never, ever thought
would happen, he never
thought would happen and
they never planned for that.
It wasn't supposed to happen.
He was five years older. They
were both in great shape.
So he's having a very hard
time still after a year
accepting that she's gone and
going on without her, yeah.
- Gloria was my wife. We
had 56 wonderful years.
We were on a camping trip,
it was on the Loyalsock River
and I'm helping her up
on a boulder with me.
Without her, I would have never
developed into any kind of a man.
She was my strong right arm.
She is the driving force.
She is my agent. She is
just about everything.
- She fished too.
When he proposed to her, only
Joe Humphreys would do this,
he put the ring in a fishing license
and I believe presented
it to her that way.
She figured out a long time
ago that if you can't beat 'em,
join 'em and she knew that there was no
holding him back and
that that was his passion
and she was by his side
quite a bit on the stream.
- My mom, she just was this shining star
and she brought out the best in all of us.
- I was so lucky.
The memories come back so strong.
- Just stay there and read or whatever,
just fall asleep and I thought
I have to do something.
She said "Focus on something."
"Oh, somewhere in this favored land,
the sun is shining
bright, bands are playing
somewhere and somewhere, hearts are light.
Somewhere men are laughing and somewhere
children shout but there
is no joy in Mudville,
mighty Casey has struck out."
- Gloria died a year ago, May 20th.
- It was a hard day
acknowledging the year
mark that she left us.
It was appropriate to
be at the Inn because
we had been there with her
shortly after her diagnosis.
- The Aaronsburg Inn is where Denny
and I stayed when we fished
Penns Creek each year.
Denny and I were there
when we found out that
Gloria had cancer and she can't be cured.
It was gone too far
and so I had a bit of a breakdown
the last time we were there.
I'm all right.
- With Gloria passing,
there's me trying to
provide support to Joe now.
Ironically I think most
people including myself
would have looked at getting
out on a stream as being
a part of the healing process
and initially Joe withdrew.
He did not want to be on a
stream, he did not want to fish.
He was suffering too much.
Then I got the phone call.
"Let's go fishing."
- There you, there you go.
Oh, that's a better fish.
- Yeah, that's a good fish.
- I saw the color on that guy.
- Oh boy, I'll take him.
- Very nice, huh?
Gloria would be happy. She
loved it when we went fishing.
- The secret of
life is having something
exciting to look forward to,
that is the secret of life
and fly fishing is that,
you're going fishing.
- 90% of the time
when we fish together,
I'm not fishing, I'm just
standing next to him.
Why would I possibly want to
be 50 feet down the stream
doing my thing when the
living legend is right there?
- Yay.
Hey.
- Well I'll tell you, we couldn't have had
a better start than we did,
it's been a good half hour.
- There is a sense
of healing with fly fishing
and this sport has come back
and helped him heal too.
- This is one of the last stands
of virgin timber in Central Pennsylvania.
It's one of my favorite spots.
I'm a tree hugger.
These were the game trails
and those were the trails
that the Indians followed.
These trails later on
became roads, highways.
I love the sound of this little stream.
I love the sound of the
water, it's therapy for me.
How picturesque, how beautiful.
What a gift to be here,
just to witness this.
Let's eat.
It's almost hot dog time, it's
getting closer and closer.
- Cheers.
- Cheers, Denny.
- Pretty amazing lunch spot.
- Yeah.
I've had lunch here with Gloria
and we've had some memorable times here.
Walked the forest trail
and reminisce and plan
our future and talk about the
good times and what adventures
we may find ahead of us and
the moral of the story is
enjoy your mate as much
as you can while you can
because they can go quickly.
I'm very lucky to have lived this long.
So I'm very happy to face another day.
Jack, Joe Humphreys.
We're going to Pennsburg to
shoot for the veterans today.
Okay, talk to you later.
- How'd you do that?
- I fell at night.
That's why I don't fish at
night by myself much anymore.
Take this along, let that
dry and hope it works.
I'm out of here.
I have volunteered with
Project Healing Waters
for many years and there
are many chapters and units.
They'll be having breakfast
but they won't want
to get down on the stream
too early with this fog.
Are we here, are we ready?
All right.
- There he is.
- I made it.
- This is hard to
see but that's the flak jacket
I was wearing when I got shot,
my buddy took that picture.
- Whoa, thank God you're here.
Thank God you're all here.
Fly fishing's the greatest
therapy in the world.
These waters and the fish
they're catching within,
it's a healing process.
- Fly fishing for me has been a way for me
to concentrate and to focus on something
because I have a very
active and racing mind
with PTSD and it's hard for me to relax.
I can get out of a bad state
of mind and reel myself back in.
- When did you get into this game?
- When I was 10 years old, my
father introduced me to it.
- Oh, neat and you had some
good times with your dad?
- Yes sir.
- Isn't that wonderful?
Let it drift.
Pull, ha, ha, ha.
I see another one, ah, ha, ha.
All right, all right.
We're wading these rocks, think
how many thousands of
years they've been there.
Oh my god, now you might have
to adjust your casts just a little bit.
One of the things that'll
really help you on this one,
the rod tip doesn't go far,
it just goes way up high.
Just two inches, okay?
And then I shock and then I
drop it and it just stacks it.
Then it's just floating on its own
and all that leader's
doing the job for me, okay?
Catch me a fish.
A big fish, a big fish!
Yo,
keep him, yay.
Oh, what a lovely fish.
Whoa.
I am gonna tear my fingers
to pieces but I don't care.
Do you have us?
- You just made my whole-
- You made my whole year.
- Oh, Joe.
- Whoa.
- You see the way he smashed that?
You'd never think that piece
would hold a fish, would you?
- Penns Creek.
- On a dry fly.
- Thank you so much.
- Georgie, I am having the time
of my life. I'm so excited.
This is a day I will never forget.
- Sometimes I feel that
the streams and rivers run through me.
- And the flow of the
waters, it's been my soul,
it's been my heart and
I want to protect it.
- In Pennsylvania, the top
industry is agriculture.
The second is tourism and
people come to Pennsylvania
to fish our beautiful
streams, hunt in our woodlands
and enjoy the beauty of Pennsylvania.
Economically, it's smart
to save what we have
and fly fishing is a big part of it.
All of these streams bring people from
all over the world to fish
here and unfortunately,
there are so many threats
that are facing the streams.
The drive for the Marcellus
Shale and the disruptive
activities of strip mining
can ruin a lot of waters.
It's a never ending battle
and we have to stay on our
toes to keep our waters clean.
- Here's the thing about Joe,
he's mister conservation
as far as I'm concerned.
Anything that comes off
the roads gets dumped
right into here which gets dumped into
the Duck Pond gets
dumped into Thompson Run.
- Which dumps into
Spring Creek, right.
- We'll improve habitat in the stream
but if we don't get a
handle on stormwater-
- If you don't have water
quality, what good is the habitat?
- Right, exactly.
- You don't have any trout.
- Exactly.
- My major conservation effort
is Thompson Spring and the Duck Pond.
This is why they call
Spring Creek Spring Creek.
There are a myriad of
streams along its course.
This is one of the main ones.
Thompson Run is a big, beautiful spring.
It is a major producer of cold water
that gives Spring Creek its life.
This is Thompson Spring
that comes right out
of the bowels of the earth
right up through in here.
This is the future of
Spring Creek right there.
Just adjacent to it is a
pond called the Duck Pond.
The Duck Pond is a storm
sewer runoff holding pond.
You have chemicals, mercury,
oils, every contaminant
imaginable that flows from
the streets of State College
and surrounding areas
going into the Duck Pond.
In the early 50s, they
relocated the highway and that
relocation pushed Thompson
Spring into the Duck Pond,
pushing all of that contaminated
water into Spring Creek.
See where the arrow is, the turning arrow?
That's where the stream was.
We had brook trout, brown trout.
When it rained, we'd run into
the iron furnace to get out of the rain.
So it's hard to believe that
the trout stream was there.
They just took the whole
thing and just shoved it.
The water temperature started to climb
to the 80s and 90s, killing the fish.
Spring Creek went down as a major
trout producer and as
a viable great fishery.
Seeing its demise was heartbreaking
because I had so many
wonderful childhood memories.
I couldn't stand it and so
I said what can I do myself?
What can one man do?
In the early 70s, I
pulled five guys together,
we sat at this table right here
and formed Spring Creek Trout Unlimited.
We determined that we would divert
that big spring back around the Duck Pond.
We are at the top of the Duck Pond.
What you're seeing right
here is the diversion
as it goes up the whole way
paralleling the Duck Pond
and to the right is the
spring, the water from
the spring, coming down
through into the Thompson Run.
It was a nightmare to divert Thompson Run.
This concrete wall is what we had.
You can see the thickness of it here.
With an air hammer, a jackhammer,
we punched a hole through it.
Then I needed a huge pipe to go through
the hole that we were
making to divert the spring.
The water flows through and
comes down the other side.
Spring Creek came back on its feet.
It was a major undertaking
for a few crazy guys
that didn't know when to
quit, we beat the odds.
- That had to be incredible
to watch all of your
efforts actually happening.
- It was a dream coming true.
I saw the salvation of Spring Creek.
The retention dike has eroded.
A good third of Thompson Spring is now
entering the Duck Pond,
which we've gotta correct.
People are aware of what is happening now.
The guys from the Spring Creek
Chapter of Trout Unlimited,
the University, they are
backing me to get all
the trees and all the
vegetation cut off the dike,
brush out the area and make it
accessible so that you can reconstruct it.
It takes a lot of thought and a lot
of effort from a lot of
people to get it done
and this is what I'm
hoping, that it can happen.
One of the most famous paintings
in the history of this
country is right here.
I'm sure it would probably
go for millions today.
This picture right here
is the westward movement,
the covered wagon and the oxen
and this was done by Joe Humphreys,
his name is there, in 1939.
We might put that on "Antique Roadshow."
Now here is an interesting,
this is an interesting,
in fact this is my
grandfather, Thomas Humphreys.
My grandfather was in the Civil War.
This is the famous Bucktail unit.
They were the snipers, the sharpshooters.
My grandfather was captured
outside of the swamps of
Richmond and was held in Belle
Isle Prison for three months.
Very few people survived three months
at Belle Isle because
there was nothing to eat.
Then he went on a prisoner
exchange and went back
into battle and he
bought in South Mountain
and then at Antietam, he
got down in behind a stump,
eased himself up over the stump to take
another shot and a bullet
came and caught him
in the mouth and came out his neck.
He was 50 years old
when my father was born.
He survived and that's why I'm here.
- I'd say the Humphreys
are a pretty strong breed.
- Yeah, I think we have some grit.
I'm not one to quit and
I have staying power.
Do you care if I fish up above you here?
- Are you Mr. Humphreys?
- I am.
- I'd be
honored just to watch.
- Well, thank you.
I'm tenacious until my goal is fulfilled.
That's a deep hole.
Will he do it? Some say yes.
That he has positiveness.
Nice fish, I want to hold this one.
Beautiful.
Look at the colors, the stripes.
- Nice fish.
- Yeah, but he got my nymph.
I knew I should have doubled the knot.
- Live and learn, Joseph.
- We have another shot here.
Here's a parr rainbow, look
at the parr marks on it.
Ain't he a beautiful little thing?
I am still going to take a 20 pound brown
if I have to come back from
another world to do it.
I will find a 20 pound brown.
- Through the years of knowing Joe,
he only knows one speed,
110%, give it all you got.
There is no quit in that guy at all.
- When I was
filming on the White River
and on the Little Red in Arkansas,
John Wilson was with me and I hooked what
we thought could have been
a new fly rod World Record.
It was an absolutely huge
fish, well over 20 pounds.
- It was over 30 inches.
- Oh, huge.
- I saw him roll in the light and-
- The memory still is burning within.
It's been 10 years and I'm
going back to Arkansas.
It's called determination.
I'm gonna catch that damn fish.
Let me show you something.
In 1992, Rip Collins took this 40 pound,
four ounce brown trout out
of the Little Red River.
I've hooked huge fish in
this river on two occasions.
Both times, they beat me.
But a biologist told me,
"Either in the Little Red
or the White, there could
be a 50 pound brown."
A 38 pound brown trout
would be a fly rod record.
I'm still pursuing this record.
To take a fish like this would
be a dream of a lifetime.
- The water is extremely
high, it's flood stage.
When my friends inquired
at the local tackle shop,
they said "Go home, the
river is unfishable."
We got a fish.
- Wow. That is
a beautiful fish, Joe.
- It's pretty but it's not big.
We need big, we need big.
Yeah, we got some weight on this one.
There's a nice fish.
- Come on Humph, come on, come on.
- When I'm nymphing and I'm
into the deeper, heavy water,
lots of times I'll simply not adjust what
I'm fishing as much as I do the length
of the leader and it
will make a difference.
That'll get a little more
time on the bottom naturally.
Let's get a big one.
- Wow, Joe.
- That's a minnow.
We're looking for a 20 pound brown.
I'm gonna try to get down on the bottom.
Take it, go on.
I got a fish.
Oh yeah.
- Nicely done.
- I just have a feeling
that it could happen.
- I thought for a second it might've been-
- Oh, I thought it might've been too.
- You can't be discouraged in
the fishing game or no
matter what you do in life.
Sometimes we don't understand why things
aren't going smoothly but nothing is easy.
You have to be flexible.
Looks good. That streamer
looks really good.
Let's see what they do with this egg.
If you're persistent and stay
with it, it'll pay off in time.
Not a bad fish.
I knew there was a reason
I didn't sleep in today.
Now you go and tell your
daddy that I'm here.
What are you doing out there?
- Catching fish.
- You're going down the river.
- Is that Joe?
- How you doing?
- I'm well.
- I am well too.
I caught a trout.
He knew me, didn't he? He called me Joe.
Hey James, good morning.
- Good morning, sir.
- How are ya, buddy?
- Good.
- You're on your feet and
you're moving, that's good.
This is December 15th, our last day
for the quest of the 20 pound brown.
So far we've been shortchanged
but with the luck of the
draw and any luck at all,
we may take a heavyweight,
which is always the quest.
Thank you, John. Thank you.
We're gonna give it our best shot.
I'm not quitting.
I'm after that 20 pound brown
and it could be in front me.
You never know when
that fish can be caught.
We were working the
shoals very successfully
and we were continuing to catch fish.
- First nibble of the day, Joe.
- But as the day was coming to
an end, we made one more run.
That was a good fish.
- It's getting pretty dark.
- I had worked all day
and this was literally
the last moment before we had to go back.
My fly is a large sculpa,
it's drifting and I'm
lifting and it stops.
I feel the head shake.
If the fish goes upstream,
they're usually pretty good.
It's a heavy fish.
This was the trout,
this was my dream trout.
Yeah, that's a good fish,
this is a happy fish.
This is the fish of a lifetime.
This fish is so heavy, I
cannot move it from the bottom.
I've gotta stop this fish.
There's a stump in there somewhere.
- Is he still on?
- I don't know.
- Huh?
- Go above him.
- Is he running into the weeds?
He's got you in something.
- .
- Wow.
- He took me down into the weeds.
Holy, that was a big fish.
A big fish like that,
they know the bottom.
He went under, there was a stump or a log
or something up there or the
grass he went back under.
I thought we had him, I really did.
When you can't lift a fish,
when you can't turn a fish,
I've never had a fish
that I couldn't turn.
I couldn't turn that one.
I couldn't put any more pressure
on him because he was playing me.
But that's something that you hook a fish
that big, you don't even get to see him.
- But you could feel him.
- Oh my yes, yeah, I did.
That trout, if we had landed it,
would than not have been
a real sport spectacular?
And we had the chance
because we hooked the fish.
God, just heavyweight, just like a log.
Just like a freakin' log.
It was like hooking onto the
Trident submarine and it's
running around in the ocean
and you have no control.
To take big fish, you can
do what you know to do
but you have to have some luck too.
- You were really close.
I'm sorry.
- That was the fish.
- I know, I know.
I'm heartsick for you.
- One of the things that
I've done since childhood
I guess was to decorate
under the Christmas tree.
Rather than trains or Christmas gifts,
my father put together something under
the tree and so I continued the tradition.
I'd get the moss from the
forest and it keeps rather well.
It's the American Indians
and the animals that
were here pre-Columbus.
I've collected the animals and
the Indians over many years.
Some of those little figures
are probably 70, 80 years old or older.
At that time in early America,
we had the buffalo and the Indian here
and he's maybe trying
to catch this rabbit.
Well, the Indians have to
have water and let's face it,
their livelihood depended
upon the fish within
and somewhere in my lineage,
there must have been
some Indian blood because
I sure do connect with
the American Indian and what
he went through to survive.
I get a kick out of doing it, it's fun.
I guess that's still the little boy in me.
A lot of these are going
down and this is coming up.
In the off season when I'm not fishing,
hunting is what I really enjoy.
There's a couple there.
Come on this way, come on baby.
You have a lot of thoughts
when you're hunting.
I think about how fortunate
I am to be here, to do this.
It's hard to believe how
time, how quickly it passes.
I know that I'm 87 and how
fast my life is scurrying on.
I'm here at the top of a ridge.
I was happy and thrilled
to be able to climb it
but how many more years
will I climb this ridge?
Hopefully a few more.
At this late stage in my life,
I'm still building memories.
Whether it be that big
buck someday or simply
an eight inch brook trout on
a wonderful mountain stream,
you always have those
things to look forward to.
There's a real purpose in life up here.
I guess that's the solitary aspects.
It encompasses all of those things.
These are my reflections
when it's awfully quiet and nothing moves.
- Okay, are we ready?
I better get the new hat on my old head.
It's cold out there.
Turn on the damn heater.
January, February and March
can be long, cold months.
Here we are in the winter,
we've got snow but I
also have cabin fever.
- There's times when I just
have to be on that stream.
I'm going fishing.
- There's nothing like
a beautiful day on a trout stream.
It's something that in
those cold winter months,
it keeps you alive and
it keeps you coming back.
- There's one in this corner
back over in here if I can get it.
We got a fish.
But to catch a fish like this, yeah,
this is the cure for cabin fever.
How was that?
Without water quality, you don't have fish
and they have to have a food
chain, they have to eat.
So everything we can do to keep
the contaminants away
from the clean water,
we have to do it and it starts right here.
It starts at home, it
starts with Thompson Run.
Good morning.
- How are you?
- Look at me. What do you think?
- You look good.
- There are trees
growing in the diversion.
They have to be taken out of there
so that we can start the
reconstruction of the dike.
If you can't see what has to
be done, then it won't happen.
- You're amazing, Joe.
- A lot better than it was.
- Do it this way, this is
a dream come true to me.
That's a piece of the slag
right from out of the old iron furnace.
You can see it now.
It is mind-boggling what
can happen when you have
a group pull together to do a
job with the right equipment.
There we go there, there's
the man right here.
This was a tangled mass of brush
that turned into a lovely area.
What a wonderful day it has
been, how much we accomplished.
Stage three will be to get the machinery
to the site to further
reconstruct the dike.
There's a lot of work
to be done and if I have
to be that driving force
along with TU, so be it.
- My father does wear
his heart on his sleeve.
He treats everyone like family
and he has so many friends.
- His house, it's Grand Central Station.
- Oh my god, anybody comes in now.
- It's always been fun.
At any given time, people are at the door,
the phone's ringing nonstop,
somebody stops in for a visit,
somebody comes for happy hour.
- It's happy hour time.
- I've said to him before,
if you judge a person's
character by the company
they keep, then he is the
wealthiest man I know.
- That's a filet.
We will turn these six minutes on a side.
You want 'em medium-rare.
Every year the night before
the first day of trout season,
a group of us have a major
happy hour and a major feast.
Everybody come out to
the dining room table.
This is the kickoff of the 2016 season.
Here's to the opening day of trout season.
Take a bite of the strawberries
and the whipped cream and
then chug with the champagne.
Yeah.
We start in The Corner
Room at eight o'clock
and have breakfast when
everybody else is fishing.
Two pancakes and a side of bacon.
And then we go to The Bald Eagle.
The randoms are popping off I imagine.
- And I've got a secret
weapon I bought yesterday.
- Ooh boy.
- What do you think?
Which one?
- I like that one.
I've been fishing every year
the first day since I was six years old.
This is my 81st opening day.
- Ah, there's my first hit.
- You taking a rest?
- I wouldn't miss
this opportunity to see you fish.
- Oh, true to heaven.
- That was fun, we caught some fish, okay.
Come on, children.
We fish only a couple hours because
we have to be to the
Hot Dog House by noon.
I'm ready for the Hot Dog House.
Everybody then ordered a
Mr. Hot Dog with everything.
Jeff, he wimped out and had a salad.
Now we fish Spring Creek
and now we wish parts of the Bald Eagle.
Andy has a fish.
- A thing of beauty.
Thanks, Joe.
- You're enjoying
a cigar, where's Joe at?
- Right down yonder and
he keeps catching fish.
- He's always the last one off the stream.
The oldest and the last one.
- I've had 81 opening days of fishing.
81 years.
Some of these trees aren't 81 years.
I don't know of one dog
that's 81 years old.
I don't think there's a
chicken that's 81 years old.
- Oh, I think there's a chicken.
- Show me, Ron.
You know what time it is?
Oh, it's a quarter to
6:00, we've gotta go home.
This is frightening.
To Jim's we must go.
Give me a break, all right.
- Here's to tradition.
- Here's to Joe.
- Our Joe.
- Gracious host.
- All of us are gonna struggle
and work to survive until 2017.
- All right.
- Oh yeah.
The streams of PA are waiting for you.
Okay.
- Thank you very much.
- Good, good.
- I appreciate that.
- God love your heart, you bet.
That is so cool, I'm very proud of you.
- Thank you very much.
- You're doing a great job.
- Appreciate it.
- And I don't want you to get hurt.
- No.
- Okay.
- Yeah, me neither.
- We need to get a group shot.
- Yeah.
As you know, one thing I love to do,
it's gonna be tradition,
we're gonna start now,
I want to night fish tonight.
- Jesus.
- No, I'm serious.
I want to night fish.
- You are serious?
- Yeah, we are going
back and I know there's
one spot in Spring Creek
I think we can take fish.
- What about
the cookers, remember?
- It worked, oh no, oh my
god, we're all exhausted.
Why are we? Please no.
This is our first day of trout season.
It is not so much fishing,
it's just bringing together
at the different eating establishments
as well as fun on the stream.
- You were convincing.
- Yeah, hey Tom, I might
get an actor or anything.
- Yeah.
- If people today had to go through
what you did to figure
out how to catch fish,
I don't think people
would be doing it today.
If you let failure stop you,
you would have stopped long ago.
- Yeah, that's what makes it fun.
Those fish are not gonna beat me.
No matter what happens,
I'm gonna beat these fish,
I'm gonna make it happen.
Like the Clint Eastwood movie where
the Indian said "I'm going
to endeavor to persevere."
Ooh trout, you're dead.
You poor a little fellows.
The Green Drake is a magnificent insect.
One of the largest mayflies
we have here in Central Pennsylvania.
It's an indicator of your water quality
and the Green Drake is
adverse to pollution.
A lot of streams don't have Green Drakes
because they don't have the water quality.
The Green Drake hatch happens once a year.
I call it the Memorial Day Classic.
It's hard to predict
when it's gonna happen
and not all fly fishermen are successful.
It's such a phenomenon
because the life cycle
of that fly really stirs
the fish into activity.
It's one of my favorite times to fish.
A mighty stream, isn't it?
Isn't it beautiful?
- It's absolutely,
what a clean stretch.
You know what I've heard
you say? "Look up."
- Isn't that beautiful?
- That's awesome.
That's pretty good, it's gonna get more.
They're gonna get lower.
- Nice fish, Humph.
That's a wild brown.
- If only we could all do this at 87.
With Green Drakes, stand in
this stream and throw flies like that.
- Yeah.
- Life is good, Humph.
- Life is good.
You can follow the hatch
but it's also great when
you hit the hatch in its
later period of production.
we just happened to really nail it right.
Welcome to the Green Drake hatch.
- This is what we
have been waiting for.
This is when the flies are in profusion
and the fish are ready to feed.
It's an exciting time of the year.
I'm going out and catching fish.
- We don't have
enough stuff to bust 'em
but I think I might be able
to take one underneath.
But let's just get one good fish.
- There we go.
- Nice.
- There we go, this is
good, this is what I need.
- That's awesome.
- I'm turning it.
Yeah.
- That a boy, Humph.
- Yeah, I'll take him.
- A nice 15, 16 inch trout took the fly.
Yeah baby, that's all
I needed was one fish.
Green Drakes flying, fish on.
- It's a good night, Humph.
- It's a great night.
What could we ask for that
was any better than that?
- That was as
good as it gets I think.
- As you grow older, you
appreciate what you have more
and I think trout streams
are fountains of youth.
It's that challenge to
try to take that fish.
It's always a learning situation.
I will never lose that excitement
of going on a trout stream.
Every day on the stream is an
adventure and as a teacher,
if I've passed some good
things onto other people,
not only the how-to, the nuts
and the bolts of the fly fishing game
but an appreciation of nature itself,
that's what it's all about.
- The person that
made this possible was Joe Humphreys.
- There is gonna be a day that's gonna
have a Green Drake hatch on Spring Creek.
You can never anticipate which
way your life will take you,
the people you will meet along the way,
the journeys you'll go on.
You have to follow your passions in life.
That's what it's all about.
- Through my life of fly fishing,
there were a culmination of moments that
cast memories such as a cast in a thicket,
a jumble of brush on a mountain stream.
When a cast seems
impossible, then it happens.
To see the fly land and bounce
jauntily for a brief moment,
then disappear as a
brook trout inhales it,
this is the moment down deep in my gut,
a feeling of satisfaction,
joy and contentment.
The melody continues to play
through my heart and soul.
It's orchestrated by the water
and the wind moving the hemlock past.
Right now age-wise, I'm
17, 18, I'm having a blast.
Beautiful casting.
Nicely done.
- I know.
- When you were four years
old, this was how we did it.
Good, good.
Beautiful cast.
She is following the wonderful
casting tradition of all of you.
- How many
tickets you got in there?
- I use this cut a lot when I fly.
We are going to land
where there's unbelievable
ground trout that will be
the new fly rod record.
- We learned from
last year, didn't we?
- 25 degrees at 4:00 in the morning.
You can't be a wimp and
be a night fisherman.
Good fish.
- Look at the camera.
- That was a big fish.
- These waters are filled with
miles of endless memories.
They're my childhood, my family, my career
and my inspiration to pick up a fly rod.
The Springs, they're my heart,
their waters the course of
my life story and the trout
the friends I want to see
flourish for a lifetime to come.
- Hold on here.
We're gonna do these last two.
- Okay.
- Okay?
- "I had the honor of
fishing on Pennsylvania
Creek with Joe about nine or 10 years ago.
This was a birthday
gift from my dear wife.
I spent a couple of days with
a Jedi, Joe as I called him.
He not only taught me something
about nymph fishing but
he shared his soul with the
love he has for creeks, streams,
rivers, fish and the
conservation of all of the above.
It was a masterclass in
living life in harmony,
respect and humility
for one's environment.
I came away from this retreat
cleansed and invigorated
and had learned a couple
of fly fishing techniques.
I shall never forget him and that weekend.
Oh, and we caught some
beautiful trout as well,
all released back to
those crystal waters."
Who said that?
Who said this?
- Liam Neeson.
- Oh, did he?
Liam Neeson said this?
Oh, he's such a wonderful man.
I taught him to tie a fly
and he tied a beautiful dry
fly, a collector's item.
Jedi Joe, that
caught me right in here.
Then wiggle and then it comes down, okay?
What the hell was that?
- It was a mill, we grew up in a mill.
That's the excuse for my odd behavior.
- Don't you think she
sounds, you sound like dad.
- We do have similar
facial expressions, I must say.
- You can go up the stairs
up there and pet the bear.
I wrestled a bear about that size.
He hooked my leg and I couldn't get out.
- Joe Humphreys here.
- Denny and I
had a good day in the
stream, I hooked two trout.
I don't know what he was doing
in there but I hooked that beaver.
I don't know too many guys
that can hook land beavers
and so I can put that on my
resume as a beaver catcher.
- A nationally-known
expert on the art
of fly fishing, a gold
medalist in our hearts,
ladies and gentlemen,
fisherman Joe Humphreys.